Guide to the William Oland Bourne Papers 1837-1881 MS 69
New-York Historical Society
William Oland Bourne papers
1837-1881
New-York Historical Society
Bourne, Wm. Oland (William Oland), 1819-1901
MS 69
0.75 Linear feet
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, newspaper clippings and lectures related to the career of William Oland Bourne (1819-1901), a social reformer, editor and author in New York City. Of particular note are materials related to his publication, Soldier's Friend, a newsletter for Civil War Veterans through which Bourne organized a Left-handed Penmanship Contest for veterans who had lost their right arm. The collection contains photographic portraits of four of the contest participants, left-handed writing samples and a sample written with a prosthetic arm. Material related to left-handed penmanship is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital copies of material related to left-handed penmanship are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Arrangement
The William Oland Bourne Papers are arranged chronologically in three series:
Series I: Soldier's Friend
Series II: Labor
Series III: Manuscripts, Lectures and Articles
Historical Note
Born during the nascent abolitionist movement in the United States, throughout his professional life as a journalist, editor and author in New York City, William Oland Bourne embraced social reform causes related to the anti-slavery movement, labor and civil war veterans' rehabilitation. The Bourne Papers, which are suggestive of an evangelical orientation and advocacy for temperance, demonstrate Bourne's considerable passion for his causes through his writing as well as the fervent responses it elicited from peers and readers.
Four broad areas of Bourne's professional life are documented. The first is the publication of Soldier's Friend, a newsletter focusing on the stories and needs of Civil War veterans. A proponent of education and rehabilitation, Soldier's Friend sponsored a Left-handed Writing Contest for veterans who had lost their right arm. The collection documents this event including four portraits of competing veterans, left-handed writing samples and a sample written with a prosthetic arm.
Additionally, the collection covers Bourne's involvement with the Workingmen's Democratic Republican Association and his related publication, The Iron Platform. There is documentation pertaining to the formation, operations and dissolution of the American Mining, Metallurgical and Manufacturing Company and the Humboldt Mining and Manufacturing Company. Much in Bourne's handwriting, these materials include letters, copies of agreements and memoranda of his meetings with firm officials from 1859 to 1860. And lastly, the collection documents Bourne's literary and oratory work in the form of unpublished manuscripts and copies of lectures.
Scope and Contents
The William Oland Bourne Papers consist of a range of materials both hand-written and printed. These include agreements, articles, broadsides, correspondence, leaflets, lectures, manuscripts, memorandums and newspaper clippings related to his advocacy for the laborer and disabled civil war veterans. The collection contains several unique items which include four photographic portraits of disabled civil war veterans who participated in the Left-handed Penmanship Contest, left-handed writing samples and one sample written with a prosthetic arm.
Agreements; Articles; Broadsides (notices); Correspondence.; Leaflets (printed works); Lectures.; Manuscripts (documents); Memorandums.; Photographs.; Editors.; Social reformers.; Antislavery movements -- United States.; Disabled veterans -- Rehabilitation.; Iron platform.; Mining corporations -- United States.; Mining industries -- United States.; Penmanship, Left-handed.; Soldiers' writings, American.; Tariff -- United States.; Working class -- United States.; United States -- Economic conditions -- To 1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Portraits.; Soldier's Friend; American Institute of Mining, Metallurgical and Manufacturing Company; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Platforms; Humbolt Mining and Manufacturing Company; United States. Army -- Military life; Workingmen's Democratic Association
- Series I. Soldier's Friend, 1864-1872 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I consists of correspondence, leaflets, articles and broadsides related to Soldier's Friend, a newsletter for the Civil War Veteran. It contains several unique items which include four photographic portraits of disabled civil war veterans who participated in the Left-handed Penmanship Contest, left-handed writing samples and a sample written with a prosthetic arm.
  Arrangement Note
  Series I. Soldier's Friend, is arranged chronologically.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital copies of material related to left-handed penmanship are available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
  - Correspondence, 1864-1872 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Left-handed Penmanship Papers and Photographs, 1865-1868 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II. Labor, 1852-1881 (Box 1)
  Series II consists of correspondence, memorandum and agreements primarily hand-written by Bourne related to the formation, administration and dissolution of the American Mining, Metallurgical and Manufacturing Company and the Humbolt Mining and Manufacturing Company. Some of the names frequently mentioned are: Frederick Janes, E. C. Benedict, Frederick V. Rushton, Andrew C. Armstrong, Francis Bourne, Joseph E. D. Comstock, Albert Gilbert, Daniel B. Brown, William S. Sears, John N. Wyckoff and Samuel Clark all of whom apparently had related operations in New York City, Virginia and California.
  Series II also contains broadsides, brochures and correspondence pertaining to Bourne's involvement with the Workingmen's Democratic Republican Association and his related publication, The Iron Platform.
  Series II. Labor, is arranged chronologically.
  - Records of the "American Mining, Metallurgical and Manufacturing Company" and the "Humbolt Mining and Manufacturing Company", 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Records of the "American Mining, Metallurgical and Manufacturing Company" and the "Humbolt Mining and Manufacturing Company", 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Workingmen's Democratic Republican Association / Broadsides and Brochures, 1852-1872 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Workingmen's Democratic Republican Association / Correspondence, 1855-1881 and Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III. Manuscripts, Lectures and Articles, 1837-1870 (Box 2)
  Series III. consists primarily of unpublished, hand-written manuscripts including Bourne's unpublished book, Out of Work: or, Walks Among Empty Workshops and Dreary Firesides written in protest against the Tariff of 1846 and describing the conditions which Bourne cited as the result of this commercial policy. There is a volume of four lectures given at the Beriah Sacred Lyceum entitled: The Effects of Ignorance and Education (March 30, 1837), The Effects of Christianity (December 28, 1837), On the Study of History (December 1837) and The Origin and Progress of Idolatry (July 1838). There is a set of newspaper clippings some written by Bourne, which were originally folded into the back cover of the volume of lectures.
  Series III. Manuscripts, Lectures and Articles, is arranged chronologically.
  - Volume of Lectures, 1837-1838 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1851-1870 and Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Unpublished Manuscript "Out of Work", Part I, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unpublished Manuscript "Out of Work", Part II, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Untitled Manuscript, Circa 1864 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript "The American Laborer as an Artist", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript "The Dweller in Ambervale", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript "Fighting and Working", Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Two Untitled Manuscripts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)